<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>top10nl on Clarity</title>
    <link>https://justobjects.nl/tags/top10nl/</link>
    <description>Recent content in top10nl on Clarity</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2008–2018, Steve Francia and the Hugo Authors; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 11:56:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://justobjects.nl/tags/top10nl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>GPS Hiking and The Evolution of Navigation</title>
      <link>https://justobjects.nl/gps-hiking-evolution-navigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 11:56:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justobjects.nl/gps-hiking-evolution-navigation/</guid>
      <description>
        
          &lt;p&gt;On sunday August 25, 2015 I provided a talk/workshop for a local knowledge network of friends and acquaintances in Amsterdam. TLDR; see &lt;a href=&#34;http://gps.justobjects.nl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;gps.justobjects.nl&lt;/a&gt;
. Originally, I would talk about &lt;em&gt;“Hiking with GPS”&lt;/em&gt;. But as I started pondering about this subject I decided to broaden the content to include also the evolution of navigation. My reasoning was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by using GPS we unlearn navigational skills such as compass and map reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my personal interest in human evolution for example the route humans followed out of Africa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/out-of-africa.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Routes (red) of Homo Sapiens out of Africa to populate the World&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I combined all these elements into a new title/subject &lt;em&gt;“GPS Hiking and The Evolution of Navigation”&lt;/em&gt;. See also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/justb4/wandelen-met-gps-en-de-evolutie-van-navigatie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;these slides&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural Navigation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I was already reading and practicing the intriguing art of Natural Navigation which in short allows one to find direction without any device nor map. By reading and interpreting signs of nature one can determine direction, i.e. where The North is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natural Navigation is not just about finding direction by sun, moon and stars, but in particular by interpreting our natural surroundings, i.e. the land, the plants, the trees and animals. Natural forces shape these surroundings, making them asymmetric under the influence of their prevailing forces. This asymmetry in nature provides clues for example where the North is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.naturalnavigator.com&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&#34;lazy&#34;
      src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/tree-combined-wind-growth.jpg&#34;
      alt=&#34;Left tree shaped by wind, right by the sun (src: The Natural Navigator, Gooley)&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance: sun, rain and wind strongly shape the direction that trees and their branches grow. A prevailing south-western wind will bend trees slightly north-east.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also mosses and lichen on trees give clues about direction. This has saved me once in finding my way when hiking on a cloudy day without GPS and an emptying smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started with Natural Navigation I recommend the books by Tristan Gooley via &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.naturalnavigator.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;www.naturalnavigator.com&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.naturalnavigator.com&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&#34;lazy&#34;
      src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/book-tnn-gooley.jpg&#34;
      alt=&#34;The Natural Navigator by Tristan Gooley&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also intrigued in how early humans navigated. As hunter/gatherers we had to cross enormous stretches of land, often going far out from a base camp for a hunt or food collection. Did these first humans use dogs for navigation, made landmarks?They sure must have been masters at Natural Navigation. We can get some clues from indigenous people today. Years ago I read a fascinating book &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Songlines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;“The Songlines” by Bruce Chatwin&lt;/a&gt;
, which in short told how Australian Aboriginals could navigate throughout their continent, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Songline&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;as Wikipedia explains&lt;/a&gt;
:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Within the animist belief system of Indigenous Australians, a songline, also called dreaming&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;track, is one of the paths across the land which mark the route followed by localised ‘creator-beings’ during the Dreaming (creation time, JvdB). The paths of the songlines are recorded in traditional songs, stories, dance, and painting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/songlines.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A knowledgeable person is able to navigate across the land by repeating the words of the song,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;which describe the location of landmarks, waterholes, and other natural phenomena.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going Outdoors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/lezing-foto-1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;GeoCaching and Natural Navigation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended the session by doing an exercise with both Natural Navigation and following a route and GeoCaching with GPS. Here my &lt;a href=&#34;http://gps.justobjects.nl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;Map5.nl&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a href=&#34;http://app.map5.nl/nltopo/?key=gast&amp;amp;gpx=gpx/vliegenbos238.gpx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;NLTopo App&lt;/a&gt;
 appeared useful for those without GPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;float_left&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://app.map5.nl/nltopo/?key=gast&amp;amp;gpx=gpx/vliegenbos238.gpx&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&#34;lazy&#34;
      src=&#34;https://justobjects.nl/uploads/2015/08/nltopo-app.jpg&#34;
      alt=&#34;The Route and Caches in the Map5.nl NLTopo App&#34; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was fun afternoon, maybe something to reenact in another setting. Let me know if you are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the landing page of this talk/workshop at &lt;a href=&#34;http://gps.justobjects.nl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;gps.justobjects.nl&lt;/a&gt;
 and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/justb4/wandelen-met-gps-en-de-evolutie-van-navigatie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;slides on Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;
. In Dutch but you may view the &lt;a href=&#34;https://translate.google.com/translate?sl=nl&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;js=y&amp;amp;prev=_t&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fgps.justobjects.nl%2F&amp;amp;edit-text=&amp;amp;act=url&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34;&gt;page via Google Translate&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;

        
      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
